PIXAR IN A BOX 艾墨镇 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox
- So far we've been exploring what a software engineer
那刚刚呢 我们了解了下皮克斯的码农都是干啥的
does at Pixar, which is creating the tools used
主要就是为电影制作些工具啊
in the filmmaking process, such as a hair simulator
比如头发模拟器
and all the parameters artists can't control.
还有所有供艺术家使用的参数
The person actually using these tools in each film
而最终用这些工具的人
is known at Pixar as the Technical Director.
就是传说中的TD
To better understand this kind of work,
为了更好地了解这个工种
we've invited Jacob Brooks, a technical director
我们请来了Jacob Brooks
who has used hair simulation in our films.
他就是使用模拟器的人
Hey Jacob.
你好Jacob
- Hey, how are you?
你好 别来无恙啊
- Pretty good, so you worked on Spot for The Good Dinosaur,
挺好的 你曾参做过the good dinosaur里的spot
- I did, I did, yeah.
是的
- So were the artisticals for Spot's hair?
同样同样也有spot的毛发
- Well Spot was one of those characters that you knew
是的 spot是那种
we wanted to fall in love with right away.
我们想你一看到他就不行不行的角色
So he had a lot of appeal in him,
所以他有很多特性
but he also kind of straddles that world of being
但他也是那种穿越了整个狂野的世界的角色
in the wilderness so he's gotta wild and a little unkempt.
所以会有些野性和不羁
So with his hair we were able to kind of bridge
所以在他的毛发上 我们想能体现出这种东西
those two worlds so that you can still get that feeling
能让你感觉到
of kind of a matted tangled, kind of wild animal feel
那种毛糙的野性的动物特质
to him but also get that appeal of like,
但同时又能体会到
just a child that wakes up in the morning
初生婴儿般的
and has adorable bed head.
美好与可爱
So it's just super familiar to us.
让我们觉得有熟悉感
So for the hair, as far as the texture goes,
所以毛发设计上 从材质来看
we knew we were gonna have to have strands
我们知道我们要有线
that were intertwining and felt like they hadn't
要看上去凌乱
been washed in a while, not going towards that gross
没洗过 没梳理过
factor but something that definitely feels
不是完全的乱七八糟
entangled and unkempt, but also just kind of hit
但必须不羁里又带着温存
those shapes that we knew that we'd want to just
有一个清晰地轮廓
frame his face nicely and be appealing,
来突出他的脸型 体现他的特征
so that he does have that genuine appeal in the film.
他那种真实的特质
- So how did you model the hair to meet these artisticals?
那你是怎么给头发建模来实现这种艺术表达的呢
- Well before we can actually simulate the hair
在我们能进行毛发模拟前
on a character that's moving, like Spot as he's running
对于这样一个角色 他在电影里的移动跑动很特别
around in the film, we actually have to groom the hair,
我们得先梳理他的头发
we have to model that shape, and for Spot,
我们要建模出他的发型
it was an interesting challenge because his hair
对他来说是个不小的挑战
is so tangled it becomes a very important thing
他的头发很凌乱 这是很重要的
to make sure those hairs aren't intersecting in weird ways
要确保他们不会以奇怪的方式打结
and that you can feel that the hairs are actually
但你会感觉到头发证的互相缠绕
twisting around one another, in order to do that,
为了实现这一点
we ended up using a technique that was developed
我们使用了一项迪斯尼的技术
at Disney Animation where we're using geometric tubes
几何管
to shape gross shapes in his hair,
我们用这个技术来获得毛糙的发型
so that you can really get the appeal
你能获得每束头发的特征
of individual clumps of hair, and see how it tapers along
并且看到他的末端
towards the end of the hair, so with those tubes,
如何逐渐变细 所以借助这个技术
once they're shaped in a certain way,
只要他们定型了
we fill those tubes with curves, and those are the curves
我们就在管道里填上曲线
that we end up simulating as we go forward.
而这些曲线就是最终我们要模拟的
- Now that you had the shape that you wanted,
现在你有了你想要的形状
how did you set up the hair simulation to get
那如何来设置模拟
the look that you wanted?
来获得你想要的形状呢
- The sim of the hair for him is obviously
他的头发很明显有些不同
a little bit different as well because you've got this
因为你有这种
mangled mass of hair, it needs to hold that shape,
扭在一起的的部分 它需要保持它的形状
and it doesn't move like even your hair would
它也不像你的头发那样
or someone with straighter hair, so it doesn't hang
或有些直发的那样 它不会
with gravity like you would think, as a whole for Spot,
因重力下垂 整体来说
his hair is a little tighter than most of our hair,
他的头发更紧
the springs are a little bit tighter so that you don't
所以他的弹簧也会紧一些
get quite as much sag and it really does feel
这样你就不会搞得很松垮 他看上去真的
like it's been teased and frazzled and kind of holds up
就像被玩弄过然后乱糟糟的 挺在那儿
and defies gravity a little bit more than natural
较自然的长发而言
like longer hair would be.
它对重力的抵抗更强
- [Interviewer] So Spot had variation for his hair.
但是这个角色也有另一种发型吧
Like when he was wet, so how were you able to do that?
比如打湿后 你们怎么做
- Because he was in the wilderness and we knew
因为他是野生的 所以我们知道
there was a bunch of weather changes where sometimes
总会有一些天气变化
it's starting to rain, sometimes it's in the middle
比如有刚开始下雨 有时候被浇了一会儿了
of the rain where it's getting heavier,
有时候是暴雨
and sometimes he's soaking wet
'cause he gets in the river,
有时候就是完全打湿 可能他掉进河里了
my colleague David Liley and I worked on something to where
我的同事就是琢磨该如何入手的
we started thinking hey, wouldn't it be cool
我们就像 能不能通过调整参数来实现
if we just changed simulation parameters to get the hair
我们对头发不同状态的模拟
that he started with to be the hair as it changes.
当头发变化的时候
And so he started on the soaked version of the groom,
所以他先从完全打湿开始
and by changing things like the stiffness of the springs
通过改变弹簧弹力系数
we could lose that groomed shape that was all spirally,
我们能让螺旋状的发型松垮
it would make it kind of flattened out,
然后贴到别的东西上
we would turn up the gravity so that it hanged
然后调高重力
a little bit tighter to his face.
他就紧紧贴在脸上
So what that allowed us to do was change the simulation
所以我们可以通过改变模拟参数
parameters a little bit at a time,
来调整我们需要的效果
so maybe gravity would get a little bit stronger
重力再强些
or the springs would get a little bit looser,
弹力松些
so that you can get a variation of that transition
你就能得到从干到湿之间的一个数值分布
from dry to wet, but you had various stages in the middle
这就能形成各种各样的中间效果
that you could get which normally if we were just doing
这样你就能获得每一个头发的效果
independent grooms, we would have more of this kind
然后我们设计了各种开关
of on and off switch, of like, it's dry, it's wet,
干 湿 干 湿 就像这样
now we can get a nice blend through that range.
现在我们就有了混合效果
- That's pretty cool, thanks Jacob for coming by.
这很酷 谢谢
And now onto lesson two.
接下来是下一课 aimozhen.com/pixarinabox